You're telling Chad, hey, how would I
find the largest file on my hard drive?
It could give you the command, but it
cannot run the command on your hard
drive. By tool use, we're able to just
bypass all of that and let the model
have sort of like a side channel where
it is saying, okay, these are tokens
that I'm not emitting for the user to
read. Stop for a second. You should run
a certain function or a certain tool.
The tools combined with the context and
the model and the agentic harness around
all of that is the thing that makes an
agent an agent as opposed to sort of
like just the model which is like a
brain in the jar. It cannot do anything.
the 41K versus the 1.1K between Claude
and Codex. That's super significant.
Talk us through kind of like I guess the
[music] split in the tools. Our sense is
that Sonnet 45, Opus 45 do better than
the Codex models [music] in using other
tools. There is reason to believe that
the model would be capable with new
tools that it's never seen because it's
like more of a generalist as opposed to
has been trained on [music] those tools
in particular.
Before we jump into this episode, I
wanted to let you know that this podcast
is for developers building with AI at
the core. So whether that's exploring
the latest tools, the workflows, or the
best practices, this podcast's for you.
A really quick ask, 90% of people who
are listening to this haven't yet
subscribed. So if this content has
helped you build smarter, hit that
subscribe button and maybe a like. All
right, back to the episode. Hello and
welcome to another episode of the AI
native dev. Um, and my name is Simon
Maple. I'm your host for today. And
joining me is Yaniv Acne.
>> Hi. And Yian is a software engineer from
Tessle. Yaniv, you've done a huge amount
of research um on some super interesting
things about, you know, understanding
how context can be used to better enable
some of the top tier uh agents in our
industry today. Um, you're a software
engineer. you've done a little bit in in
the AI engineering space. Tell us a
little bit about yourself.
>> Yeah. Uh thanks Simon. So um I've I've
been with Tesla since the start. I think
we joined the same time give or take. Uh
I've done a bunch of roles and basically
change role and shift shape to to fit
whatever is necessary. uh I've I've led
and kind of like started the I
engineering team but now have uh focused
more on working with customers but still
in working with customers sometimes
understanding uh what could best service
customer or how would whatever context
is relevant to a customer would fit in
with an agent requires us to actually
often times we look at what customers
are doing but sometimes actually look at
what the agents are doing and seeing how
the two things fit. So what what context
do do the agents come with built in like
when when you when you download cloud
codeex gemini and so on what is it what
is actually told to it internally and
then you see how do you fit whatever
you're whatever else you're feeding to
it externally to see the two things kind
of like gel well together.
>> Yeah.
>> So that's been the the the underlying uh
thought behind the research right like
let's see what is in those agents what
is being told to them. So let's talk
about
>> and you gave this as a lunch and learn
here in the office. Uh in fact there's a
lunch and learn happening right now uh
from Maria who actually was on the
podcast gosh um well actually uh last
week in fact she it was released last
week and she's yeah giving a another
wonderful uh session today. You gave
this session a week ago uh as a lunch
and learn
>> at lunch and learn
>> and we thought wow we were blown away by
the information first off and then we
were like oh we should we definitely
have to get this on the podcast we need
to share this um but this information is
is for our own for Tesla's really own
knowledge initially it wasn't something
that we were originally going to share
um it was for our learnings right
>> it's so so we started looking into this
I I can't remember when did we start as
soon as Tesla started basically as soon
as agents appeared we definitely started
looking at how do they work kind of like
packaging it up a bit and and preparing
for presentation was for for a meetup
that was happening here in London and
then we said okay maybe we'll do like an
extended director's cut for lunch and
learn and then afterwards we said hey
maybe there's content for a podcast here
so let's do that cool
>> so here we are
>> so we're going to we're going to kick
off with I guess a little bit about
about some baseline statistics for
agents some of the some of the top tier
agents that I guess most people of our
listeners would probably uh maybe use
today then we're going look at what kind
of things will actually change that
performance, better enable agents to
perform their tasks uh more effectively.
Everything from looking at system
prompts to the to the information that's
given um in a prompt. Uh then looking at
things like the tool usage, what tools
are available to agents and how that
affects uh their their capability uh and
more. So where do we start unique?
Should we have a look at the the
baseline for how uh how agents work
today? If I can like one thing we we
should remember before we we'll we'll
talk exactly about about the baseline or
like the
>> the [clears throat] agent with nothing
in it basically to start with right like
yeah but before we do that just just a
quick reminder to everyone uh we're
doing this to best understand what
context to give agents
>> we we cannot speak on behalf while we're
talking about like flagship agents that
you may have heard of. We can't speak on
behalf of those companies. Uh we don't
have any internal material from them.
We're trying to understand how to best
use uh the product we're being given and
uh and so some of the things we say I
hope they're right they might also be
wrong. If you have a different
perspective if your understanding of how
say Claude code or Gemini works like
please uh let us know and and we yeah
it's we're showing you the research as
it's happening basically.
>> Absolutely. Sounds good. Let's jump in
>> with this. Let's let's go to the the
minimalistic agent. Right. Yeah. Okay.
So, uh on the screen, what we can see
here is um the code for something I
called nano agent in for for the meetup.
I basically vibe coded in like an hour.
There's there's nothing particularly
interesting here
>> other than the fact that there is
nothing particularly interesting. Like
the interesting thing is that this is a
working coding agent that uh I wouldn't
say uh would win you any awards uh but
is actually quite capable. Quite
capable. So,
>> this is Python, right?
>> This is in Python. I wouldn't say it's
quite capable and it's, you know, it's
>> it's not as capable if we wrote it in a
100 lines of Java.
>> There we go. At least 100 lines.
>> At least 100 lines of
>> and then some library and some XML.
Exactly. Exactly. To get started. Okay.
But no, but but in Python, this is what
I wrote. And frankly, I think I could
have done without the write file and
read file tools. I think just execute
and the run agent loop would have been
enough. But if if we look at the the the
bits here, we have the system prompt
which which you can read is like 250
bytes and it just says hey you're a
coding agent do well and the execute
commands allow the the model to run any
command on whatever is the environment
this is running on. I'm running it in a
container and then write file and read
file because I felt that will be uh
easier for a human to understand that if
we would have seen the model doing an
execute command and trying to like you
know echo something into something or
cat something to read a file. So just to
have explicit tools for read and write
would probably be okay uh even with just
execute but maybe the the heart of the
agent is the run agent uh function where
we see we're initializing the model
we're giving it the tools right like the
other functions are given to it as tools
I'm using here the a library called LLM
by Simon Willis great library in my
opinion
>> and then we're creating a conversation
where we're starting with the system
prompt and whatever the user has told
the the agent to do so like the goal and
now the agent runs in a loop saying okay
what can I do to achieve this goal and
we're counting on the model the
underlying model that we're using to
power this thing uh this I I ran it with
sonet 4.5 but whatever recent model
you'd use to say oh well given this goal
and given this prompt and given that I
have this tool I need to understand
what's going on here I need to start
reading what files already exist in the
file system I need to run ls I need to
run a read I need to understand what's
going on and then start actually getting
towards the goal. If I tell it make me a
to-do app, I need to start writing
files. I need to execute a test. I need
to check that things are working until
eventually uh this wild tool calls and
the number of available turns uh is
done. So there the model saying I don't
want to call any more tools or we've ran
out of turns and then we have something
complete.
>> Mhm.
>> So that's it. And in a 100 lines you get
an agent and you're thinking, well, it's
probably not a very capable agent, is
it?
>> And I I can't say it's very capable. I
mean, I'm sure it's not very capable,
but if you if you you ask it to, hey,
make me a to-do app. Don't over
complicate it. This is for a demo. Just,
you know, put something nice on the
screen and make it look good and so on.
You get a working to-do app from this
like underund line uh agent. It looks
great. It works. Like you click around,
you can manage your to-dos. I don't
know. You can vibe code with this. Uh I
wouldn't say as well as you would with
the flagship agents, but but absolutely
works and provides good results. Mhm.
>> And this isn't a new observation that
that I've made or I don't know Tesla
have made. Like I said, I wouldn't say
it's a very capable agent, but if you
actually look at the scores for a
terminal bench, uh terminal bench, a
popular and I think quite a respectable
uh benchmark.
>> We use it we use it internally.
>> We use it also internally. Exactly. For
for EVOs that that we run.
>> Uh you see there only 15th place. So
okay, not first place and not second
place but not 100th place. only 15th
place is mini sui agent uh from the same
lab that made su bench and and su agent
and so on and uh you see that they have
minu agent which is also under 100 lines
they do 100 lines for the the core
agentic loop and then I think they they
give themselves another 100 lines for I
don't remember if it's tool use or
something else but still you can read
the code in one sitting very very
comfortably
>> and yet it gets to a very respectable
15th place and also if you see kind of
like the distribution of scores is it's
not like 15th place and really really
far below 14th place or 13th place. It's
it's actually uh in a pretty good cohort
and I would say uh maybe on par maybe a
bit below uh actual like serious agents.
So what is what is this telling us is
the kind of like the thing which makes
agents
you know that much better.
>> Based based on this uh alone I would say
well looks like maybe tools and context
are not that important
>> because uh even with very little tool
with very little tools and with very
little context look at 100 lines you
don't have much to work with.
>> Uh you can you can get to a good score.
Mhm.
>> Uh so uh you you might think that it
could also suspect that that there are
things that terminal bench doesn't
cover.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. And at the end of the day,
benchmarking is an art and an extremely
difficult and like challenging task to
do like really well.
>> Uh perhaps there are real world
situations where uh the the flagship
agents the the the big brothers of many
agent would do better because they have
this additional context, additional
tools and and so on. M.
>> So, uh, is it that context doesn't
really matter? If it doesn't really
matter, how come the flagship agents all
come with loads of context? And
actually, what kind of context do they
come in with?
>> And the context you're talking about the
question we're asking.
>> And the context you're talking about
here is specifically the system context,
right?
>> Correct. Correct. I I should be clear
about that because when we say context,
we usually mean the context that you add
to the agent, right? So we we don't
usually think about the context that
comes built in in the agent
>> and that is primarily the system context
and tool descriptions.
>> Yes. So uh if if you're thinking about
the the the the call that being that's
being made to the LLM, there are certain
amount of input tokens
>> at the end of them is somewhere as
though it doesn't have to be the end
typically at the end would be the user's
request. Make me a to-do app.
>> But first there's a lot of uh your cloud
code or your Gemini or your codeex.
You're a helpful agent. This is what you
do. This is how you behave.
>> Here are all the tools available to you
and for each tool this is the schema of
the tool. This is the description of the
tool. This is when you should be using
the tool. So this is exactly kind of
like what we'd like to be looking into.
>> What do the big labs choose to equip
their agents with like the built-in
context, not the context that is being
added to it.
>> So what do they choose to put built in?
What uh descriptions and what tools do
they choose to make available and how
does that affect um agent performance
and how does that affect
>> and of course colleagues will give
>> to add some context if you don't mind
the pun. I'm sure you enjoyed that.
>> I do mind the pun but you know you know
we've been working together for a while.
>> Once it's out I can't take it.
>> Exactly. Exactly. to to add some overall
context to the research. What you're
interested in or what and what Tesla is
interested in is of course adding our
own context or adding context that uh
allows the agent to perform a certain
task then better and it's additional
agent which is very uh core to that task
so that the agent has a better chance of
actually being able to complete that
task. Whereas the system is kind of like
a generic context that just makes a
perform
here going to be next focused on system
prompt and the system context. I'd love
to kind of like you know learn some of
your findings in in that system context.
And we said the the reason we're looking
into it is that at the end of the day
when you're doing when you're invoking
the model
>> all of that context gets mixed together
and the model it gets mixed together in
some order with some words that would
describe here is the section that you
should be reading in this sense or
whatever but still it all gets mixed
together and gets shipped to the model.
>> So you need to understand the the
built-in context. I don't know that
there is a term of art for this but the
system prompt and the tool descriptions
in order to add your own context. At the
end of the day, the whole thing gets you
to including the user prompt and
including everything and the model needs
to start creating output tokens. So we
we better understand these things to
learn from the big labs. Probably they
know what they're doing in terms of
creating tools but also to be compatible
with the big labs and ensure that the
context we're providing doesn't
contradict and sits well with the
context that we know is there.
>> Yeah. So we can effective is that
>> so we can be more effective in our
external cont.
>> What I love to call uh mechanical
sympathy. It's understanding what is
under the covers. Like I don't need to
understand I don't need to understand a
gearbox how it works perfectly in order
to use it because my use of it is
literally using the the you know the
gear stick but as a formula 1 driver
them understanding how it works under
the covers will actually make allow them
to get every benefit of that of and so
this is essentially
>> 100% 100% right like know where are the
studs when you want to hang a picture
right like you need to understand what's
behind the wall.
>> Yeah exactly. So uh if you want to look
I want to look at context I want to read
the system prompt
>> um you can but depends how how you do it
how would you extract and so on but you
you can because it's English right if if
you've read a book you can read the
system prompt right
>> but also it's pretty difficult to show
it in a podcast because it's not that
interesting as like showing someone
reading a book or I I could show you the
pages of the book to the camera.
>> It's interesting to to talk about size
first like yes that's something we can
talk about in a podcast. Uh we're
talking about around 12 kilobytes of
context that we've seen in claude.
>> Yeah.
>> Around uh 10 kilobytes of context I mean
specifically system prompt. 10 or 10.7
kilobytes that we've seen in codeex
>> and around 14 14.7 kilobytes that we've
seen in Gemini. And obviously they're
they're adjusting this a bit as the
versions of these agents change. I don't
know if that's exactly what what you'll
be seeing for your version but that's
roughly the the amounts we're talking
about 12 10 14
>> and Claude and Gemini here. We're
talking about claude code and Gemini
CLI.
>> Correct. Correct. Yeah. Should be
clarified. Exactly.
>> But now, okay, so 12 kilobytes, 10
kilobytes, 14 kilobytes, about 12 pages
of text.
>> What what goes into those pages of text?
I felt that this visualization, right,
like the the tree map with colors is a
useful way to to give you a sense of
what is in the system prompt without,
you know, sitting down with a book and
reading it.
>> Mhm. So uh to to me this is like
creating a sort of like an index or a
legend for for the book and giving you a
chance to see out of the system prompt
how many words were spent talking about
uh the process or how the agent should
work versus about safety versus about
how to communicate with the user uh how
to write tests and so on and so forth.
Right? Like you can see the the tree map
on the screen. the difference is is
quite you know you would you would have
thought
>> yes
>> they would have similar learnings as a
result have kind of like similar splits
particularly with some of the biggest
ones that they've got but looking here
>> I mean you look at the two biggest
sections on Claude it's different to the
two biggest sections on codeex and then
with Gemini actually it uses one of each
of the biggest two it's it's surprising
how different they are
>> the the the difference was surprising to
me that's [clears throat] True. And
especially surprising given that in the
back of my mind I keep remembering sort
of like the null hypothesis or the the
zero agent, right?
>> It also works without any of this stuff.
So what makes them put in 10 kilobytes,
12 kilob, 14 kilobyt when I'm knowing
that it works pretty well. Like
>> I imagine there needs to be quite a lot
of value in in the system prompt for
them to bo to put it in.
>> Uh so I don't know exactly why are the
differences as they are. I think you can
look at the chart yourself and sort of
like have have a sense for what you're
saying. You can go and read the text
yourself and have a sense for what
you're saying. But um to me like reading
it as as an outsider uh it's it felt
like there are certain properties or
traits that the model came out with out
of training and out of after
reinforcement and post- training and
everything
>> and were things that the the the lab
wanted to emphasize or wanted to subdue
a bit. Right? So all prompts talk about
be direct, be clear, do not waste tokens
like uh follow follow the instruction of
the user that kind of thing. But now I'm
making a hypothesis. I don't know. uh
maybe there's more about uh use of tests
uh in claude than in the other agents
because they felt that after the model
came out of training it needs a bit more
leg up on tests or there was uh more
about um the the the process and how to
manage your work right like when I say
process I mean making to-dos or how how
to decide how to plan ahead because
after training uh for Gemini and Claude
they felt they wanted to to assist the
model more. Yeah. So that's my it's I
don't know if that's a very good way to
think about it, but a bit like a patch
in software, right? Like you're patching
the bits where the model didn't do
exactly as you wanted. So you're giving
it a leg up using the context, using the
system prompt.
>> And of course, we can't like directly
compare each of these to say, oh,
Claude's doing it this way, Codex is
doing it that way. Because of course,
they're different models as well. So the
different models are going to act
differently and potentially require
different support in different areas or
different direction rules in different
areas to be able for both of those
models to actually achieve the same
thing. So this obviously specific to
each model as well but incredibly
curious which were you most surprised at
would you say? Um I think I think for me
the way uh the way that Claude manages
process and manages planning
>> uh was quite distinct from Codex and
Gemini and doesn't necessarily even uh
is not so visible in the chart. Codex
you can see there's very little on
process. Gemini there's more but it's uh
differently framed and like used
differently. We'll see that again a bit
further on when we talk about tool use
and the tools uh that are available to
to each of these agents and how does
Claude use the to-do tool very
differently to to the other uh two
>> but also Claude leans very heavily on
the idea of sub agents and on delegating
tasks to sort of like a separate agentic
loop with its own context and its own
use of tokens. M
>> so saying okay you go and do this task
for me afterwards I don't care what what
context you've built while doing the
task I just care about the result and
I'll continue from there and um Claude
is using that in the most flexible
manner I would say
>> and that's captured in the process
presumably or is it more in the tools
process okay
>> would be useful to to say a word about
how do they come up uh with with these
dream maps uh basically taking the text
of the system prompt and then uh sort of
like asking a model to come up with a
classification for every line in the
text.
>> So if if we switch to to another slide
for example is it's it it looks like a
bar chart but it's not really a bar
chart. I' I've used a bar chart to
represent the text. So imagine that
every pixel is a word or a letter. I
don't remember which I've used and uh
the the labels that I've added are the
things that are determining the color of
the line. So it's a bit like the mini
map in in your editor like many VS code
and other editors often have like this
mini map of the code on the side with
syntax highlighting. So this is not
syntax highlighting. This is context
classification category highlighting.
>> So for every line we're adding oh this
is about coding philosophy. This is
about an approach to testing. This is
about safety. This is about process and
whatever. And then we're coloring the
lines appropriately.
>> Mh.
>> You get a sense for volume and for line
length. You can see how many lines there
are and how long they are. Mhm.
>> Not hugely different, but somewhat
different. And you get a sense for um
what are the lines about, right? Like
the label that that we see through the
color [clears throat]
>> and and we see these like substantial
differences.
>> Yeah.
>> I've also seen some things that I I
don't know why these things were added.
It's it's it's curious, but I've seen
some things that I felt were surprising
in the sense of an instruction to uh
only follow like only allow certain
kinds of tasks, especially around
security, right? You should not be used
for offensive uh security tasks. You
should only be used for defensive tasks.
Um evenarding
>> safeguarding. Yeah. Even in capture the
flag or like um like penetration testing
exercises, only do that with appropriate
authorization. just the text reads a bit
weird. I don't know how will the model
know that there is appropriate
authorization.
>> Yeah.
>> What are we imaging that looking like?
Like that the agent will ask me, hey, is
this authorized?
>> I'll say yes.
>> And is it still fair to say that a user
prompt
>> kind of is essentially part of the same
ultimately context as the system prompt
when it goes to the model. And so I
think um gosh maybe a year ago when when
um I think it was GIO who had a previous
session with uh with someone uh Caleb
Sema he talked about how the data plane
and the control plane um you know all
the information in the context was was
pushed into the data plane including the
the system context including the user
context and any data and it's very hard
for the models to be able to work out
the difference. Is there still that that
that danger of course that any context
we add on top whether it's whether it's
a user prompt whether it's any
additional context and data that's
really just getting mushed alongside the
system prompt and it's the model that
then has to kind of like work out what
to do with those conflicts.
>> It it's it's a great point and it's it's
an area of of active research and
development. Even the terminology system
prompt and user prompt it's it's a bit
dated at this point. uh but we do not
have standardized terminology right like
uh some developers call them the the
developer messages where there's a user
messages trying to create a hierarchy
called like hierarchy of authority you
must always do what is in the system
prompt and uh and you should follow the
user prompt only if it doesn't
contradict the system prompt you should
always follow what the developer promp
so they're trying to create this
hierarchy
um in in my experimentation and in our
our evaluation sorry um
Yes, models are getting better at
following that distinction in that
hierarchy. Better is not yet perfect,
right? And it's um
>> I think I think that this issue of um
conflation of the situation is um is
something that that models still need to
work on, right? If
>> it's it's a bit of the um how does the
the Star Wars quote uh go, right? Like
the Jedi mind trick, you have not seen
anything, right? [laughter]
So so that is something that a human
wouldn't get wrong and models still
might, right? like a model guarding at
the door. Your instructions are to let
me in. Oh, my instructions are to let
you in. That's great, right? So, still
something to get better at.
>> Okay, so we learned a little bit about
the the size of the prompts, the the um
the I I guess split between the the
style of what is in the prompt, where
they where that sits in in the order.
What was next? Did we go into kind of
like the tool usage most important?
Because if we look at Claude that seems
extremely high on the in terms of the
the the system prompt for describing how
the model should use the tools. what was
the differences in terms of
>> so I think here there's okay so if we if
we look at tools I agree with you that
in a sense was the thing that was most
surprising to me
>> uh looking at at uh these things the
system promps are are interesting and it
is it is surprising that there's a
difference such a difference between the
agents
>> but uh at the end of the day the amount
something about kind of like the the
vibe that you get from the system
prompts is pretty similar
>> tools on the other hand claude has 17
tools Mh.
>> And if you take uh just the the
descriptions and the the kind of like
the oneliner description and the
in-depth description if I remember
correctly you get to about 41 kilobytes
of of text with claw for the tools.
Codex has only seven tools, less than
half
>> and only 1 kilobyte, 1 point something
kilobyte of description for those tools
and Gemini is somewhere in the middle
with with a 12 and 11 at the version
that I've looked at
>> and and briefly just like mention what
is a tool what is what is a tool for an
LLM or an agent to use.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So if we remember sort of
like the minu agent or the nano agent
we've shown at the at the beginning
>> a model is just just the brain, right?
All it can do is receive the tokens that
that uh we're sending it and emit tokens
that it's emitting back out. Um if you
were sort of like imagine a Chad GPT
kind of thing, well before Chad GPT
itself had tools, you're telling Chad
GPT, hey um how would I find the largest
file on my hard drive? It could give you
the command but it cannot run the
command on your hard drive. You then
need to copy the command and paste it
into your terminal and be like okay now
I actually run this thing. And then
maybe there's a syntax error or maybe
there's a there's the the tool that Chad
GPT wanted to use doesn't exist. Okay,
so I'm copying the error and I'm passing
it pasting it back to Chad GPT and now
it's telling, oh well, you should be
using this other command and now I'm
copying back and forth back and forth.
By tool use, we're able to just just
bypass all of that and let the model
have sort of like a side channel where
it is saying, okay, this is not text
that I'm emitting. These are tokens that
I'm not emitting for the user to read.
These are tokens that I'm emitting uh to
tell the thing that is invoking me to
tell the program or the the agentic
harness that is invoking the model.
>> Stop for a second. You should run a
certain function or a certain well tool
is is the word we use. Here are the
parameters. Here are the arguments.
>> Once it's ran, the output from that
command execution should go back to the
model. So if the model is choosing to to
use the execute tool and it's giving the
parameter ls, it wants to run ls and now
we get the list of files in the current
directory that should be sent back to
the model. So now it has additional uh
input and now it can oh now I know what
are the files in the directory.
>> Now the model can decide what next it
would like to do.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh do a read file tool in order to read
what's in the files or do a delete file
if it thinks or edit and so on and so
forth. So the tools are actually the the
tools combined with the context and the
model and the agentic harness around all
of that is the thing that makes an agent
an agent as opposed to sort of like just
the model which is like a brain in a
jar. It cannot do anything. Now it's an
agent that can operate in the
environment.
>> Yeah. Okay. Cool. So when you then look
at that the 41k
>> Yes. uh versus the 1.1k between Claude
and Codeex. That's super significant in
terms of you're you're essentially, you
know, it feels like Claude is just so
much more enabled to to use these
various functions, be able to run these
actual commands. Um, talk us through
kind of like I guess the split in the
tools. Y
>> what what were the what were the
capabilities that that Claude has I
guess that Codeex may may miss with
these? You would you would I I wouldn't
be surprised if someone would understand
it that way. Oh, way more tools way more
powerful. But it doesn't have to be
actually there's a lot you could do with
very basic tools if you're able to use
them really really well,
>> right?
>> And we know from uh from our own use of
the tools from benchmark results is that
I don't want to be the like in a side
comment crowning the the best agent.
What does even best agent mean? But we
know that both of them are very capable
agents like flagship top-of-the-line
right. So even though they have this
very distinct difference in them
>> and I would think about it more as a
difference in philosophy.
>> Mhm.
>> Codex does a lot with little.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. It has these seven basic tools it
doesn't even have a read file tool. It
just you know if it wants to read a file
it executes a cat command to to read GB
or whatever like some a command that
will let it take something from the
file. And the descriptions for the tools
are very very short.
>> As in um if we we'll show here a few
descriptions of some of Codex's tools,
we can see it's like here's the the I
don't know apply diff tool and this is
how you use it and that's about it.
Whereas if we now look at the definition
of a tool from Claude, we can see it's a
lot more detailed.
>> Here's the tool. When should you use it?
What should you do in this case? What
should you do in that case? sort of like
supporting the model a lot more in
understanding when and how and what is
good and what is bad and giving it
examples and so on.
>> Mhm. Now uh again hypothesis I don't
know that this is true but I I believe
that this suggests something about the
underlying training of the models right
>> I don't know but I would be surprised if
Codex can achieve these kinds of results
without any kind of training for these
tools in particular
>> and we also know that that codeex at the
time of recording at least we're running
it with GPT 5.1-codex
not with the general purpose GPT5 5.1
but with a specific GPT 5.1 that was
then further uh trained and further
fine-tuned or RL to to to use these
tools and to better work for so you're
not so this is outside of the 1.1K which
is the tool description you're talking
about an actual something that's baked
into the training to allow it to use
this and the descriptions are therefore
just almost decorative so that the agent
with its training knows which ones to
use but the the core piece so so very
interesting and maybe and I guess this
you know there's there's There's a lot
of guessing here probably, but you know,
perhaps Claude has maybe had less of
that training for in the tools because
of the amount of verbosity in the uh in
the in the descriptions cuz it's
probably you're looking at around twice
as much verosity in the in the
description given you're around uh Oh,
no.
>> It's it's about 20 times. Yeah. Because
if you look at the difference in tools,
yeah, you're looking at about 20 times
more.
>> It's it's quite a lot.
>> Very interesting. Very interesting. And
of course we can speculate here because
we can't see the training but it's very
very interesting data and differences
between them. We can speculate and there
are other things that we see right like
in our own evaluations we've had better
success in and at the moment our our
sense is that uh set 45 opus 45 do
better than the the codeex models in
using other tools tools that they
haven't seen before right like custom
tools
>> and so while yes of course codeex and
claude and gemini all of them support
MCP you can add tools on top of them you
can just invoke the model in your own
code right like just we've seen in with
nano agents and give it whatever tools
you want.
>> We've had at least better success making
set make use of arbitrary new tools than
we've had with codeex.
>> Interesting.
>> Not saying codeex GPT 5.1 C codeex and
GP 5.1 in general. Not saying it cannot
use tools but not as flexibly.
>> Mhm.
>> And then there's a trade-off. What what
do you prefer? Right? Like these tokens
always being in the context, they're
expensive. They cost you something even
with with caching, right? They take some
of the the context window and and they
they cost us something. But they give
you this additional flexibility. You
don't need to retrain the model in order
to swap the tools. There is reason to
believe that the model would be uh sort
of like more capable. And again, this is
something that we're also seeing in
separate benchmarks uh with new tools
that it's never seen because it's like
more of a generalist as opposed to has
been trained on those tools in
particular.
>> Yep. Interesting. So you mentioned
before there's a difference in planning.
Um what does that I guess what does that
look like? What are the what are the
differences in planning across models
and agents?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, one thing that
that I um I lumped into planning is use
of cy sub agents like invoking a whole
separate agent. We could talk about
that. I wasn't sure if it was the right
thing to lump it into planning because
it's it's a whole very very rich space.
>> But when we say planning normally,
right, ignoring sub agents for a second,
we mean exactly this. the model is
instructed, hey, uh if it's a complex
task, don't just try to to do it
willy-nilly and and do whatever you
want. First of all, write to yourself
and there's there's a lot of research
supporting that models do better when
they first kind of like reason through
the problem and and create a plan
>> and just say what what is the plan or
write they don't say they they write the
plan and tokens out like to be added to
their context and now they'll be
following the plan.
>> Yeah. So both uh codeex and Gemini have
a tool called update plan or something
along these lines and what they do what
they do in that tool is just the the the
model is invoking the tool saying here
are the steps I'd like to go through.
These steps are then added to the
conversation history
>> and that's it. There's nothing else that
reminds the model to follow the plan.
There's nothing that would would tell
the model, oh you you've skipped a step
or whatever. anytime the model wants it
can just emit a new update plan and the
user will be seeing whatever is the
latest plan that the model has has
shown.
Um, usually the model doesn't change to
to change the plan willy-nilly. And so
if it had steps 1 2 3 4, it does an
update plan. Now I'm doing one update
plan, same 1 2 3 4, but one is crossed
out. Update plan two is crossed out. And
so and we get a sense of progression,
but actually the model can do whatever
it wants.
>> There's nothing in the uh aetic harness
that is running be around the model that
would remind it of things.
>> Claude takes a different approach here.
CL has several uh planning tools and
update plan task complete these kind of
things like more uh nuanced and the
agentic harness actually kind of like
supports the model by reminding it oh
you're done with step two let me remind
you that before you said that you should
be doing step three now and so actually
the plan is nothing it's just tokens
that the model is saying in codeex and
Gemini it gets added to the message
history and now now the model is more
likely to follow that because it sees
that in the the context that's gone by.
>> Whereas the plan is an actual sort of
like um uh element of flow control or
element of of control in in claude.
There is something that is not the
model. The agentic harness is actually
reminding it hey are you sticking to the
plan? Are you following the plan? Did
you finish the plan?
>> Yeah. So that's again pretty substantial
difference I think on something that you
can see how often agents are planning
right like planning is a very um
important aspect of of agentic behavior
>> and yet such a difference in philosophy
>> but again all of these are very capable
agents all of them end up like doing
their plans pretty well even though the
the underlying implementation is quite
different. Yeah, it almost feels like,
you know, there's no right way or wrong
way by the sound of it because different
models are picking different things and
like you say, it's such a crucial thing.
If there was one way that was kind of
like showing, you know, much better
value, you'd think all models would
navigate to that immediately, right? So,
it's probably just more the way that it
was it was a choice of implementation
versus any major um difference. But
yeah, super interesting to see such big,
you know, high-profile models just
choosing completely different ways of
doing these things and then sticking to
it as well
>> and then sticking to it. We'll see like
uh I I don't remember if it was Codex or
Gemini. One of them already is beginning
to have cuz the the the repo is is open
source is already beginning to have
changes to some of its tools to be like
more geared more towards kind like the
the rich set. So maybe they are changing
tech and like maybe they're approaching
it like they're making a change over
time.
>> Uh but yes the
>> seeing Claude and Codex that the
distinction is is so big between them.
>> Clearly they thought about it like this
is not the first version like we've been
out there for some time and there's a
marked difference in philosophy.
>> This isn't their first LLM rodeo is
>> yes the first Exactly.
>> So now we're going to go behind the
scenes. We're going to see some demo.
We're going to see what happens uh
behind the scenes between the agent and
the LLM.
>> Exactly. Take it away.
>> So uh to start, there's nothing uh like
incredibly novel here, but still we need
to understand the setup a bit and and
what we had to do in order to to
understand the communication between uh
the agent and the model. Um we have like
this small open source tool called
contain agent. Not not a huge amount
there, but basically uh drops you into a
container
>> mounting the current working directory
inside the container.
>> The container comes pre-installed with
many popular agents and you can run
stuff there. Very very basic like many
many other things like it around.
>> Yep.
>> Um probably other other tools like it
also have such features. I don't know.
But it's something that we've spent a
bit more effort on contain agent is
everything around proxying or
transparent proxying of uh the the
agentic harness to model traffic
>> when we're doing the recording.
>> So if I do contain agent here, I just
get dropped into a shell and now I can
do ls here and like okay there's there's
nothing much here. Uh but if we do
contain agent dash dump uh claude hello
man-in-the-middle dump
we're getting the same thing. I'm
getting jumped into into the same
directory. Now I'm in the container and
so on. But the difference is that now uh
MITM proxy the the the transparent pro
well the proxy multi-tool that can do
all sorts of proxying has been started
in the background and the environment
variables have been set so that the the
agent uh will proxy its traffic through
uh through the proxy. And now if I do
something like uh Claude
and say hello world,
Claude will think about it for a bit and
then just say hello world. That's great.
I can finish my session with Claude,
close the container
and now I have this dump of the traffic
which I can later analyze.
So uh after I I have this recording I
can do like again a a simple uh script
that we've made to to parse the the
manal and uh MITM dump dump files and do
something like
this.
And now what we have under output, we
have a standardized uh JSON file that
includes uh the system prompt that was
sent to the agent, the model that was
used, the um uh the tools that was given
to it and so on and so forth. Uh we we
see interesting things like uh looking
at these things, we see how uh Claude
sends traffic to uh to the model even
when it's just invoked to start
pre-warming caches. We see how uh Claude
is using different models because it has
these different sub agents and it's uh
starting up sort of like here's the
definition of the agent that would do
code exploration and would be using
haiku and is small and fast and can
navigate quite quickly versus whatever
the main agent that is actually writing
code and is like smarter and like using
more intelligence.
>> Awesome. Thank you for sharing that and
and I guess kind of like you know this
is an initial piece of research that
that that you and the team have done.
What does this unlock now? What are the
next steps that you kind of like want to
take to to learn new things?
>> Absolutely. I think the I I say the the
the outcome of all research is that we
should be doing more research.
[laughter] It feels it feels in this
case
>> it asks more questions than give
answers.
>> Absolutely. Absolutely. I think uh two
things that that I'd be uh interested
in. One is an ablation study around
tools and around prompts. Uh I would
love to I would love to try and take
sort of like the agentic harness of of
one of the the the big agents and see
what what happens if we remove a tool
from it
>> or if we remove parts of the system
prompt or even all of the system prompt
right like take cloud code as is with
all of its tools and everything but
instead of the 14 kilobyte uh system
prompt like or 12 I don't remember how
much is closed code like uh like make it
250 bytes like minu agents right what
happens in that case so that's one thing
>> and uh the other thing I think would be
sort of like a crossbenchmark where we
take the agentic harness of uh say uh
codec cli and we we try to run it with
sonet 4.5 or vice versa
>> hypothesis if if if what we're imagining
here is true I would expect that sonet
4.5 should be able to kind of like drive
the other car better because uh our our
current understanding is more generic
and it's not as as well trained for this
particular car, but for cars in general.
>> But it would be interesting to to even
just, you know, running running a
terminal bench on it and and seeing the
results after we've done the the
rewiring of the model behind the Aentic.
>> So, yeah, cool. Cool things to look
>> super interesting and love to kind of
want to know the answer now. [laughter]
>> Also need the time.
>> Yeah, of course. Of course. Well, if
anyone if anyone any of our listeners
kind of like, you know, want to want to
want to share maybe some of their
research or or or have done similar
things, please do let us know. But for
now, Yanife, thank you for everything.
Thank you for all the all the info and
uh it's it's wonderful to see what you
and the team are are learning and
sharing. Look forward to look forward to
seeing more.
>> Absolutely. Thank you, Simon. Thanks for
>> Thank you. I appreciate it. Thank you
everyone for listening and uh tune in to
the next episode soon. Bye for now.
[clears throat]